[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is from the shorter note on dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: The word dhamma, in its most general sense, is equivalent to thing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: whatever is distinct from anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: More precisely, is what the thing is in itself, as opposed to how it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the footnote to that reads,
[SPEAKER_00]: How a thing is, is a matter of structure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is to say, of intentions, cetanā, or determinations, saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are essentially negative, whereas dhamma is positive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in term... in terms of that, then, he's distinguishing what a thing is versus, so to speak, how a thing is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it may not be obvious that those are two things that can be distinguished in the first place, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was wondering if you had anything to comment or add about how you would discern a thing from its determinations, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... That's where yoniso manasikāra comes in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, knowing how to attend a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: without making it another thing, without making it a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this particular passage you read, dhamma is anything that has a nature to manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a feeling, a thought, a perception, a memory, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is an experience as such, it's a thing, it's a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will discern, then,
[SPEAKER_01]: What that thing is determined by, by simultaneously being able to discern what's present there, within that thing, that it isn't that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the problem is, this requires quite a refined, as in proper way, of attending to the fundamental core of the arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why yoniso, manasikāra, yoniso literally means womb.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means going back to the womb, attending to the womb of the arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is simultaneously there, present, attending to its base.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what proper attention means in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem that people have is, if that proper attention is not developed and trained and discerned, what you're going to do is, when there is a, say, a thing A has arisen, instead of seeing through it into not A, still within A, but not that A, people, when they look, they overlook.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then they see B.
[SPEAKER_01]: And B is just another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when they look for the saṅkhara, for the determination of the experience B, well, they see C. Which means they're not seeing these things simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're following them in time.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're following them linearly or logically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they can't understand the true nature of saṅkhara, because if a person would understand that, that's the beginning of paticca upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the present experience of such-and-such nature, without abandoning that experience, without over-intending it, without under-intending it, you want to discern peripherally, in regard to the present experience, what else is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant in the previous video about kamma, when I said the intentionality behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: The degree of those intentions is given beforehand, as options.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not your doing, nor it is your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being able to see it on that level, you will automatically appropriate it, overly intend it, which means make it mine, which means result in acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to discern the determination of the present there is an experience of dhamma, you need to see it within that present experience of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why every paticca upādāna starts with this, this is, with two simultaneous to present things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, when you look at saṅkharas individually, not in the context of determining dhamma, there are also things, which means there are also dhammas, as the Buddha described that when he was describing the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't want to look for the content of saṅkhara or the content of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see the relationship between dhamma and that which determines it, which is not dhamma, that particular dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to see relationship between A and that which is simultaneously present, that it's not that A, but not B either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by not giving in to A, but not making it into B, by not confusing the two, you get to understand how A is presently determined, presently arisen, with presently arisen causes as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why when they asked the Buddha, he said, how did you cross...
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, you can't cross the shore by fighting the waves, by pulling backwards, by standing still.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how did you cross the shores by not fighting the waves, by not pulling backwards, by not standing still?
[SPEAKER_01]: He has crossed the stream, the river.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem people have is... because it's a form of fighting the wave.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're over-intending it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there is the Arisen Dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: A. I look for its cause, as in, I'm looking for B, to determine A.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what most people misunderstood, but it's Upāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think it's an explanation of the life, of the three life stages, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think it's, it's, it's laid out in time, from A, B, C, D, E, F, G, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, it's always, always starts with the presently Arisen Principle of, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha would elaborate differently within the same principle, depending on who he was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes, Bhaktisiddhānupāda was describing in twelve factors, sometimes in eight, sometimes in sixteen.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is the simultaneous principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: The principle of simultaneous dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you want to see what A depends upon, you can't look for B.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to look within A, which it is an A.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's about letting dhammas endure and then not looking elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not trying to over... not trying to explain the dhamma, as... not... not trying to explain the arisen thing, but allowing it to arise and allowing it to persist and endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And while it persists and endures, you get to see what else is there within it that determines it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not that dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's saṅkhara of that dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at B, well, then you need to look now to find its own saṅkhara within that B.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like start drawing connections between A and B and then provide an explanation to yourself what the determination is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is going on to the next paragraph now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts, sabbe saṅkhara nicca, sabbe saṅkhara dukkha, sabbe dhamma anatta,
[SPEAKER_00]: All determinations are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: All determinations are unpleasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: All things are not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Atta, self, is fundamentally a notion of mastery over things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this notion is entertained only if it is pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is only pleasurable, provided the mastery is assumed to be permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: For mastery, which is essentially a kind of absolute timelessness, unmoved moving of things, as undermined by impermanence, is no mastery at all, but a mockery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, regarding of a thing, eh dhamma, as atta, or self, can survive for only as so long as the notion gives pleasure, and it only gives pleasure for as so long as that dhamma can be considered as permanent, for regarding a thing as self endows it with the illusion of a kind of super-stability in time.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, as a dhamma, regarded as atta, its impermanence is not manifest, for it is pleasant to consider it as permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it is seen to be dependent upon other dhamma, not considered to be permanent, its impermanence does then become manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: To see impermanence in what is regarded as atta, one must emerge from the confines of the individual dhamma itself, and see that it depends on what is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, sabbe saṅkhara, not dhamma, anicca is said, meaning all things that things, dhamma, depend on, are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: A given dhamma, as a dhamma regarded as atta,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is an account of being so regarded, considered to be pleasant, but when it is seen to be dependent upon some other dhamma that, not being regarded as atta, is manifestly unpleasurable, owing to the invariable false perception of permanence, of super-stability, and one not free from the conceit I am, then its own unpleasurableness becomes manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, sabbe saṅkhāra, not dhamma, dukkha, is said.
[SPEAKER_00]: When this is seen, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: when perception of permanence and pleasure is understood to be false, the notion, this dhamma is my atta, comes to an end and is replaced with sabbe dhamma anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, before you ask the question, just to... to add for that... to that is... that's... that's a commonly kind of mis... misread, when people say, oh, yeah, the Buddha said all things are impermanent, all things are suffering, all things are not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean when you kind of overly intend and... and basically use dhamma that ends up being an explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just provides an explanation that everything is impermanent and everything is not yours and everything is not yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you read... if you look at the Pali, it doesn't say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says all determinations are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: All determinations are suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: All things are not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's that... what I was discussing just a few seconds ago, that difference
[SPEAKER_01]: As in the present dhamma, present self, is determined by present things that are within it, that cannot be the self at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, go on now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was essentially what I was going to ask you about.
[SPEAKER_01]: In more... in simpler terms, if a person can make a contemplation out of it, again,
[SPEAKER_01]: A patujana thinks things are mine because I am, but it's other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you keep taking things to be for me, you keep assuming that you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, appropriation of as mine comes first, structurally, not temporally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can't have sense of self without a sense of ownership being present there, simultaneously with that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, for somebody who's understood the dhamma, sotāpanna or higher, they have abandoned that attavāda, but they still have a degree of conceit that would correspond to a degree of appropriation that they still maintain in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, ultimately, of course, they're heading towards complete freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in practical terms, if a person wants to contemplate, just take your body, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't take some random objects, because you might, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a subtle thing to understand, so you want to try as accurately as possible, you want to start as accurately as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the most accurate, the most factual thing that you have, is your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is something, your senses, that is something that everybody automatically appropriates and regards as mine, and thinks that I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I can see, hear, taste, touch, because I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you keep seeing, hearing, tasting, touching, and so on, you think you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you think you are the owner of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a person wants to undermine that sense, you can't just start explaining to yourself that this body is impermanent and use medical jargon and so on, which assumes this external point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to feel that impermanence right through the heart of that ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how you do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You do it by allowing that ownership to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: This body right here, that's present right now, sitting on the chair, talking to you, answering your questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I have this present body here
[SPEAKER_01]: Answering your question, sitting on the chair in this forest, can I do that without this simultaneous muscle inside of my chest, the heart beating and pumping blood, without oxygen being pumped around my body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I be able to operate?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without my lungs being able to breathe air, would I be able to operate?
[SPEAKER_01]: I wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means any sense of ownership, mastery, intentionality that I might exhibit,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's directly determined, simultaneously determined, or rather determined by the simultaneous presence of these other functioning things that I cannot control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's... you can't even conceive how it would be to tell your heart to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would... it's just completely involuntary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an involuntary muscle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it just works on its own, yet your whole life depends upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, many people might think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You contemplate the heart and the impermanence of it, but you don't want to contemplate it, as I said before, after, or before, or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to contemplate it right through the present thing of this appropriation of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: In another video, I was talking about that, like the simile, the simile of the chariot, how people say, ah, it's made out of parts, that is not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see the parts through the existing phenomenon of the whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the contemplation of body parts will work only, as in, it will result in dispassion, in freedom from suffering, and this disowning of your own body and your own sense of self, which means it will result in anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplation of parts will result in that, if you see it within the presently arisen basis of this appropriated body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this body that I am, these sentences I'm talking, this situation that I'm in control of, can be undermined at any second,
[SPEAKER_01]: I cannot, I cannot continue existing if these parts that comprise this entire body, if these parts, if they stop functioning, if they're dismembered, if they fail, none of which you can control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognition of that, of those determinations of those parts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognition of that, it's... they are basically impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know they might be working now, but they cannot possibly work like this in this particular arrangement forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the first recognition of the impermanence, which then in itself, well, this this cannot be pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because pleasant notion is the notion of eternity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be unchanged forever, stable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you experience the heart of your ownership as impermanent and unpleasurable, you disown it automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also another thing I want to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person who starts discerning sabhe, saṅkhara, anicca, sabhe, saṅkhara, dukkha, they don't need to then go and, ah, okay, so sabhe, dhamma, anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their experience will automatically become dhamma, anatta, sabhe, dhamma, anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be automatically experienced as not my self.
[SPEAKER_01]: This sense of self, this body, this situation, by being actually fundamentally rooted in that which is completely outside of my reach or control, undermines the ownership of this very situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, situation remains unchanged, in a way, but then everything changes because the ownership of it has been removed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why arahant cannot be necessarily recognized externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: He still acts, talks and does stuff normally like everybody else does.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no ownership of any part of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there is not any conceit or sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with regards to the example you gave of seeing your bodily situation that you find yourself in determined by the presence of, let's say, the heart...
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the way to bring your mind to this without making the presence of your heart a bee, as we said before?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without ever attending it, and then making the presence of your heart another thing, then now you're not seeing that relationship of determination anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the thing is, again, you must not become unmindful of how you feel in this present situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the present situation being felt, right here, right now, to this extent, pleasant, unpleasant, neutral, and then just start not allowing your mind to approach the notion of a pumping heart as a determination, not allow your mind to approach it as an afterthought, or as before, or as maybe as an explanation, but actually go through that situation that's being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, for most people, it's going to result in anxiety and concern, which is the inevitable beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, that's why, in the suttas you read, when people came to the Buddha and they asked him what is he teaching, he would explain the not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they would, like, fall on the ground, beating their breasts and pulling their hair in despair, that's because they genuinely understood what he was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, they did not let go of the notion of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, they experienced terror and they started... they would shout, oh, this will kill us, this will destroy us, this will obliterate us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they did actually understand what he was referring to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they misunderstood something.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be that afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sīla needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness and restraint, seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that will keep you together from falling onto the ground and beating your breast and becoming desperate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is that... that's in a matter of the ayoniso, manasikāra, of finding... determining that way to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Determining the presently... determining the present determination within the presently arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while the thing is present, you determine the determination within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not before or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while this body here, which is automatically taken as mine,
[SPEAKER_01]: Without overthinking, without making a separate experience of a thought of my pumping heart, but stay with the thought of this present experience, peripherally I discern the dependence that this experience has upon a random beating muscle of a heart, heart muscle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you'll feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll start feeling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you start feeling it, you know you're doing it right.